In this video, I'd like to talk
在这个视频中 我将会
about a new large-scale
讨论一种新的大规模的
machine learning setting called
机器学习机制 叫做
the online learning setting.
在线学习机制
The online learning setting
allows us to model problems
让我们可以模型化问题
where we have a continuous flood
在拥有连续一波数据
or a continuous stream of data
或连续的数据流涌进来
coming in and we would like
而我们又需要
an algorithm to learn from that.
一个算法来从中学习的时候来模型化问题
Today, many of the largest
今天 许多大型网站
websites, or many of the largest
或者许多大型网络公司
website companies use different
使用不同版本的
versions of online learning
在线学习机制算法
algorithms to learn from
从大批的涌入
the flood of users that keep
又离开网站的用户身上
on coming to, back to the website.
进行学习
Specifically, if you have
特别要提及的是 如果你有
a continuous stream of data
一个由连续的用户流引发的
generated by a continuous
连续的数据流
stream of users coming to
进入
your website, what you can
你的网站
do is sometimes use an
你能做的是使用一个
online learning algorithm to learn
在线学习机制 从数据流中学习
user preferences from the
用户的偏好
stream of data and use that
然后使用这些信息
to optimize some of the
来优化一些
decisions on your website.
关于网站的决策
Suppose you run a shipping service,
假定你有一个提供运输服务的公司
so, you know, users come and ask
所以你知道 用户们来向你询问
you to help ship their package from
把包裹从A地
location A to location B and suppose
运到B地的服务
you run a website, where users
同时假定你有一个网站
repeatedly come and they
让用户们可多次登陆
tell you where they want
然后他们告诉你
to send the package from, and
他们想从哪里寄出包裹 以及
where they want to send it to
包裹要寄到哪里去
(so the origin and destination) and
也就是出发地与目的地
your website offers to ship the package
然后你的网站开出运输包裹的
for some asking price,
的服务价格
so I'll ship your package for $50,
比如 我会收取$50来运输你的包裹
I'll ship it for $20.
我会收取$20之类的
And based on the price
然后根据
that you offer to the users,
你开给用户的这个价格
the users sometimes chose to use a shipping service;
用户有时会接受这个运输服务
that's a positive example and
那么这就是个正样本
sometimes they go away and
有时他们会走掉
they do not choose to
然后他们拒绝
purchase your shipping service.
购买你的运输服务
So let's say that we want
所以 让我们假定我们想要一个
a learning algorithm to help us
学习算法来帮助我们
to optimize what is the asking
优化我们想给用户
price that we want to offer to our users.
开出的价格
And specifically, let's say we
而且特别的是 我们假定
come up with some sort of features
我们找到了一些
that capture properties of the users.
获取用户特点的方法
If we know anything about the demographics,
如果我们知道一些用户的统计信息
they capture, you know, the origin and
它们会获取 比如 包裹的起始地
destination of the package, where they want to ship the package.
以及目的地 他们想把包裹运到哪里去
And what is the price
以及我们提供给他们的
that we offer to them for shipping the package.
运送包裹的价格
and what we want to do
我们想要做的就是
is learn what is the
学习
probability that they will
在给出的价格下他们将会
elect to ship the
选择
package, using our
运输包裹的几率
shipping service given these features, and
在已知用户特点的前提下 并且
again just as a reminder these
我要再次指出
features X also captures the price that we're asking for.
他们也同时获取了我们开出的价格
And so if we could
所以如果我们可以
estimate the chance that they'll
估计出用户选择
agree to use our service
使用我们的服务时
for any given price, then we
我们所开出的价格 那么我们
can try to pick
可以试着去选择
a price so that they
一个优化的价格 因而在这个价格下
have a pretty high probability of
用户会有很大的可能性
choosing our website while simultaneously
选择我们的网站
hopefully offering us a
而且同时很有可能会提供给我们
fair return, offering us
一个合适的回报 让我们
a fair profit for shipping their package.
在提供运输服务时也能获得合适的利润
So if we can learn this property
所以如果我们可以学习
of y equals 1 given
y 等于 1 时的条件
any price and given the other
在任何给定价格以及其他给定的
features we could really
条件下y等于1的特征
use this to choose appropriate
我们就真的可以利用这一些信息
prices as new users come to us.
在新用户来的时候选择合适的价格
So in order to model
所以为了
the probability of y equals 1,
获得 y 等于 1 的概率的模型
what we can do is use
我们能做的就是
logistic regression or neural
用逻辑回归或者神经网络
network or some other algorithm like that.
或者其他一些类似的算法
But let's start with logistic regression.
但现在我们先来考虑逻辑回归
Now if you have a
现在假定你有一个
website that just runs continuously,
连续运行的网站
here's what an online learning algorithm would do.
以下就是在线学习算法要做的
I'm gonna write repeat forever.
我要写下"一直重复"
This just means that our website
这只是代表着我们的网站
is going to, you know, keep on
将会一直继续
staying up.
保持在线学习
What happens on the website is
这个网站将要发生的是
occasionally a user
一个用户
will come and for
偶然访问
the user that comes we'll get
然后我们将会得到
some x,y pair corresponding to
与其对应的一些(x,y)对
a customer or to a user on the website.
这些(x,y)对是相对应于一个特定的客户或用户的
So the features x are, you
所以特征 x 是指
know, the origin and destination specified
客户所指定的起始地与目的地
by this user and the price
以及
that we happened to offer to
我们这一次提供
them this time around, and
给客户的价格
y is either one or
而y则取1或0
zero depending one whether or
y值取决于
not they chose to
客户是否选择了
use our shipping service.
使用我们的运输服务
Now once we get this
现在我们一旦获得了这个数据对
pair, what an online
在线学习算法
learning algorithm does is then
要做的就是
update the parameters theta
更新参数θ
using just this example
利用刚得到的(x,y)数据对来更新θ
x,y, and in particular
具体来说
we would update my parameters theta
我们将这样更新我们的参数θ
as Theta j get updated as Theta j
θj 将会被更新为
minus the learning rate alpha times
θj 减去学习率 α 乘以
my usual gradient descent
梯度下降
rule for logistic regression.
来做逻辑回归
So we do this for j
然后我们对j等于0到n
equals zero up to n,
重复这个步骤
and that's my close curly brace.
这是我的另一边花括号
So, for other learning algorithms
所以对于其他的学习算法
instead of writing X-Y, right, I
不是写(x,y)对 对吧
was writing things like Xi,
我之前写的是
Yi but
(x(i),y(i)) 一样的数据对
in this online learning setting
但在这个在线学习机制中
where actually discarding the notion
我们实际上丢弃了
of there being a fixed training
获取一个固定的数据集这样的概念
set instead we have an algorithm.
取而代之的是 我们拥有一个算法
Now what happens as we get
现在 当我们
an example and then we
获取一个样本 然后我们
learn using that example like
利用那个样本获取信息学习
so and then we throw that example away.
然后我们丢弃这个样本
We discard that example and we
我们丢弃那个样本 而且我们
never use it again and
永远不会再使用它
so that's why we just look at one example at a time.
这就是为什么我们在一个时间点只会处理一个样本的原因
We learn from that example.
我们从样本中学习
We discard it.
我们再丢弃它
Which is why, you know, we're
这也就是为什么
also doing away with this
我们放弃了一种拥有
notion of there being this
sort of fixed training set indexed by i.
固定的 由 i 来作参数的数据集的表示方法
And, if you really run
而且 如果你真的运行
a major website where you
一个大型网站
really have a continuous stream
在这个网站里你有一个连续的
of users coming, then this
用户流登陆网站 那么
sort of online learning algorithm
这种在线学习算法
is actually a pretty reasonable algorithm.
是一种非常合理的算法
Because of data is essentially
因为数据本质上是自由的
free if you have so
如果你有如此多的数据
much data, that data
而数据
is essentially unlimited then there
本质上是无限的 那么
is really may be no
或许就真的没必要
need to look at a
重复处理
training example more than once.
一个样本
Of course if we had only
当然 如果我们只有
a small number of users then
少量的用户
rather than using an online learning
那么我们就不选择像这样的在线学习算法
algorithm like this, you might
你可能最好是要
be better off saving away all
保存好所有的
your data in a fixed training
数据 保存在一个固定的
set and then running some algorithm over that training set.
数据集里 然后对这个数据集使用某种算法
But if you really have a continuous
但是 如果你确实有一个连续的
stream of data, then an
数据流 那么一个
online learning algorithm can be very effective.
在线学习机制会非常的有效
I should mention also that one
我也必须要提到一个
interesting effect of this sort
这种在线学习算法
of online learning algorithm is
会带来的有趣的效果 那就是
that it can adapt to changing user preferences.
它可以对正在变化的用户偏好进行调适
And in particular, if over
而且特别的 如果
time because of changes in
随着时间变化 因为
the economy maybe users
大的经济环境发生变化 用户们可能会
start to become more price
开始变得对价格更敏感
sensitive and willing to pay,
然后愿意支付
you know, less willing to pay high prices.
你知道的 不那么愿意支付高的费用
Or if they become less price sensitive and they're willing to pay higher prices.
也有可能他们变得对价格不那么敏感 然后他们愿意支付更高的价格
Or if different things
又或者各种因素
become more important to users,
变得对用户的影响更大了
if you start to have new
如果你开始拥有
types of users coming to your website.
某一种新的类型的用户涌入你的网站
This sort of online learning algorithm
这样的在线学习算法
can also adapt to changing
也可以根据变化着的
user preferences and kind
用户偏好进行调适
of keep track of what your
而且从某种程度上可以跟进
changing population of users
变化着的用户群体所愿意
may be willing to pay for.
支付的价格
And it does that because if
而且 在线学习算法有这样的作用是因为
your pool of users changes,
如果你的用户群变化了
then these updates to your
那么参数θ的变化与更新
parameters theta will just slowly adapt
会逐渐调适到
your parameters to whatever your
你最新的用户群所应该体现出来的
latest pool of users looks like.
参数
Here's another example of a
这里有另一个
sort of application to which you might apply online learning.
你可能会想要使用在线学习的例子
this is an application in product
这是一个对于产品搜索的应用
search in which we want to
在这个应用中 我们想要
apply learning algorithm to learn
使用一种学习机制来学习如何
to give good search listings to a user.
反馈给用户好的搜索列表
Let's say you run an online
举个例子说 你有一个在线
store that sells phones - that
卖电话的商铺
sells mobile phones or sells cell phones.
一个卖移动电话或者手机的商铺
And you have a user interface
而且你有一个用户界面
where a user can come to
可以让用户登陆你的网站
your website and type in the
并且键入一个
query like "Android phone 1080p camera".
搜索条目 例如“安卓 手机 1080p 摄像头”
So 1080p is a type
那么1080p 是指一个
of a specification for a
对应于摄像头的
video camera that you might
手机参数 这个参数可以出现在
have on a phone, a cell phone, a mobile phone.
一部电话中 一个移动电话 或者一个手机中
Suppose, suppose we have a hundred phones in our store.
假定 假定我们的商铺中有一百部电话
And because of the way our
而且出于我们的网站设计
website is laid out, when
当一个用户
a user types in a query,
键入一个命令
if it was a search query, we
如果这是一个搜索命令
would like to find a
我们会想要找到一个
choice of ten different phones to
合适的十部不同手机的列表
show what to offer to the user.
来提供给用户
What we'd like to do is have
我们想要做的是
a learning algorithm help us figure
拥有一个在线学习机制来帮助我们
out what are the ten phones
找到在这100部手机中
out of the 100 we
哪十部手机
should return the user in response to
是我们真正应该反馈给用户的
a user-search query like the one here.
而且这个返回的列表是对类似这样的用户搜索条目最佳的回应
Here's how we can go about the problem.
接下来要说的是一种解决问题的思路
For each phone and given
对于每一个手机以及一个给定的
a specific user query; we
用户搜索命令 我们
can construct a feature vector
可以构建一个
X. So the feature
特征矢量x 那么这个特征矢量x
vector X might capture different properties of the phone.
可能会抓取手机的各种特点
It might capture things like,
它可能会抓取类似于
how similar the user search query is in the phones.
用户搜索命令与这部电话的类似程度有多高这样的信息
We capture things like how many
我们获取类似于
words in the user search
这个用户搜索命令中有多少个词
query match the name of
可以与这部手机的名字相匹配
the phone, how many words
或者这个搜索命令中有多少词
in the user search query match the description of the phone and so on.
与这部手机的描述相匹配
So the features x capture
所以特征矢量x获取
properties of the phone and
手机的特点而且
it captures things about how
它会获取
similar or how well
这部手机与搜索命令
the phone matches the user query along different dimensions.
的结果在各个方面的匹配程度
What we like to do is
我们想要做的就是
estimate the probability that a
估测一个概率 这个概率是指用户
user will click on the
将会点进
link for a specific phone,
某一个特定的手机的链接
because we want to show
因为我们想要给用户展示
the user phones that they
他们
are likely to want to
想要买的手机
buy, want to show the user
我们想要给用户提供
phones that they have high
那些他们很可能
probability of clicking on in the web browser.
在浏览器中点进去查看的手机
So I'm going to define y equals
所以我将定义y等于1时
one if the user clicks on
是指用户点击了
the link for a phone and
手机的链接
y equals zero otherwise and
而y等于0是指用户没有点击链接
what I would like to do is
然后我们想要做的就是
learn the probability the user
学习到用户
will click on a specific
将会点击某一个背给出的特定的手机的概率
phone given, you know,
你知道的
the features x, which capture properties
特征X 获取了手机的特点
of the phone and how well the query matches the phone.
以及搜索条目与手机的匹配程度
To give this problem a name
如果要给这个问题命一个名
in the language of
用一种运行这类网站的人们
people that run websites like
所使用的语言来命名
this, the problem of learning this is
这类学习问题
actually called the problem of
这类问题其实被称作
learning the predicted click-through rate, the predicted CTR.
学习预测的点击率 预估点击率CTR
It just means learning the probability
它仅仅代表这学习
that the user will click on
用户将点击某一个
the specific link that you
特定的 你提供给他们的链接的概率
offer them, so CTR is
所以CTR是
an abbreviation for click through rate.
点击率(Click Through Rate)的简称
And if you can estimate the
然后 如果你能够估计
predicted click-through rate for any
任意一个特定手机的点击率
particular phone, what we
我们可以做的就是
can do is use this to
利用这个来
show the user the ten phones
给用户展示十个
that are most likely to click on,
他们最有可能点击的手机
because out of the hundred phones,
因为从这一百个手机中
we can compute this for
我们可以计算出
each of the 100 phones and
100部手机中 每一部手机的可能的点击率
just select the 10 phones
而且我们选择10部
that the user is most likely to click on,
用户最有可能点击的手机
and this will be a pretty reasonable
那么这就是一个非常合理的
way to decide what ten results to show to the user.
来决定要展示给用户的十个搜索结果的方法
Just to be clear, suppose that
更明确地说 假定
every time a user does
每次用户
a search, we return ten results
进行一次搜索 我们回馈给用户十个结果
what that will do is it
在线学习算法会做的是
will actually give us ten
它会真正地提供给我们十个
x,y pairs, this actually
(x,y) 数据对 这就真的
gives us ten training examples every
给了我们十个数据样本
time a user comes to
每当一个用户来到
our website because, because for
我们网站时就给了我们十个样本
the ten phone that we chose
因为对于这十部我们选择
to show the user, for each
要展示给用户的手机 对于
of those 10 phones we get
这10部手机中的每一个 我们会得到
a feature vector X, and
一个特征矢量x 而且
for each of those 10 phones we
对于这10部手机中的任何一个手机
show the user we will also
我们还会得到
get a value for y, we
y的取值
will also observe the value
我们也会观察这些取值
of y, depending on whether
这些取值是根据
or not we clicked on that
用户有没有点击
url or not and
那个网页链接来决定的
so, one way to run a
这样 运行此类网站的
website like this would be to
一种方法就是
continuously show the user,
连续给用户展示
you know, your ten best guesses for
你的十个最佳猜测
what other phones they might like
这十个推荐是指用户可能会喜欢的其他的手机
and so, each time a user
那么 每次一个用户访问
comes you would get ten
你将会得到十个
examples, ten x,y pairs,
样本 十个(x,y) 数据对
and then use an online
然后利用一个在线学习
learning algorithm to update the
算法来更新你的参数
parameters using essentially 10
更新过程中会对这十个样本利用10步
steps of gradient descent on these
梯度下降法
10 examples, and then
然后
you can throw the data away, and
你可以丢弃你的数据了
if you really have a continuous
如果你真的拥有一个连续的
stream of users coming to
用户流进入
your website, this would be
你的网站 这将会是
a pretty reasonable way to learn
一个非常合理的学习方法
parameters for your algorithm
来学习你的算法中的参数
so as to show the ten phones
从而来给用户展示
to your users that may
十部他们
be most promising and the most likely to click on.
最有可能点击查看的手机
So, this is a product search
所以 这是一个产品搜索问题
problem or learning to rank
或者说是一个学习将手机排序
phones, learning to search for phones example.
的问题 学习搜索手机的样例
So, I'll quickly mention a few others.
接着 我会快速地提及一些其他的例子
One is, if you have
其中一个例子是 如果你有
a website and you're trying to
一个网站 你在尝试着
decide, you know, what special
来决定 你知道的 你要给用户
offer to show the user,
展示什么样的特别优惠
this is very similar to phones,
这与手机那个例子非常类似
or if you have a
或者你有一个
website and you show different users different news articles.
网站 然后你想给不同的用户展示不同的新闻文章
So, if you're a news aggregator
那么 如果你是一个新闻抓取网站
website, then you can
那么你又可以
again use a similar system to
使用一个类似的系统
select, to show to
来选择 来展示给用户
the user, you know, what
他们最有可能感兴趣的
are the news articles that they
are most likely to be interested
新闻文章
in and what are the news articles that they are most likely to click on.
以及那些他们最有可能点击的新闻文章
Closely related to special offers, will we profit from recommendations.
与特别优惠所密切相关的是 我们将会从这些推荐中获利
And in fact, if you have
而且实际上 如果你有
a collaborative filtering system, you
一个协作过滤系统
can even imagine a collaborative filtering
你可以想象到 一个协作过滤系统
system giving you additional
可以给你更多的
features to feed into a
特征 这些特征可以整合到
logistic regression classifier to try
逻辑回归的分类器 从而可以尝试着
to predict the click through
预测对于你可能推荐给用户的
rate for different products that you might recommend to a user.
不同产品的点击率
Of course, I should say that
当然 我需要说明的是
any of these problems could also
这些问题中的任何一个都可以
have been formulated as a
被归类到
standard machine learning problem, where you have a fixed training set.
标准的 拥有一个固定的样本集的机器学习问题中
Maybe, you can run your
或许 你可以运行一个
website for a few days and
你自己的网站 尝试运行几天
then save away a training set,
然后保存一个数据集
a fixed training set, and run
一个固定的数据集 然后对其运行
a learning algorithm on that.
一个学习算法
But these are the actual
但是这些是实际的
sorts of problems, where you do
问题 在这些问题里
see large companies get so
你会看到大公司会获取
much data, that there's really
如此多的数据 所以真的没有必要
maybe no need to save away
来保存一个
a fixed training set, but instead
固定的数据集 取而代之的是
you can use an online learning algorithm to just learn continuously.
你可以使用一个在线学习算法来连续的学习
from the data that users are generating on your website.
从这些用户不断产生的数据中来学习
So, that was the online
所以 这就是在线学习机制
learning setting and as we
然后就像我们所看到的
saw, the algorithm that we apply to
我们所使用的这个算法
it is really very similar
与随机梯度下降算法
to this schotastic gradient descent
非常类似
algorithm, only instead of
唯一的区别的是 我们不会
scanning through a fixed
使用一个固定的数据集
training set, we're instead getting
我们会做的是获取
one example from a user,
一个用户样本
learning from that example, then
从那个样本中学习 然后
discarding it and moving on.
丢弃那个样本并继续下去
And if you have a continuous
而且如果你对某一种应用有一个连续的
stream of data for some application,
数据流
this sort of algorithm may be
这样的算法可能会
well worth considering for your application.
非常值得考虑
And of course, one advantage of
当然 在线学习的一个优点
online learning is also that
就是
if you have a changing pool
如果你有一个变化的
of users, or if the
用户群 又或者
things you're trying to predict are
你在尝试预测的事情
slowly changing like your user
在缓慢变化 就像你的用户的
taste is slowly changing, the online
品味在缓慢变化 这个在线学习
learning algorithm can slowly
算法可以慢慢地
adapt your learned hypothesis to
调试你所学习到的假设
whatever the latest sets of
将其调节更新到最新的
user behaviors are like as well.
用户行为 (字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )